<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.0.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://ianteda.com/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://ianteda.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2016-01-29T21:40:12+11:00</updated><id>https://ianteda.com/</id><title>Ian Teda</title><subtitle>Husband, Father, Engineer, Explorer &amp; Creator</subtitle><author><name>Ian Teda</name><email>ian@teda.id.au</email></author><entry><title>Leadership Styles</title><link href="https://ianteda.com/management/leadership-styles.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Leadership Styles" /><published>2016-01-29T00:00:00+11:00</published><updated>2016-01-29T00:00:00+11:00</updated><id>https://ianteda.com/management/leadership-styles</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ianteda.com/management/leadership-styles.html">&lt;p&gt;The father of leadership is arguably the psychologist Kurt Lewin, who in 1939 proposed that there are 3 styles of leadership:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Authoritarian (Autocratic)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Participator (Democratic)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Delegator (Laissez-faire)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authoritarian – rule by ones self – leader provides clear expectations for what needs to be done, when it should be completed and how to complete it. They provide vision and direction and then try to convince people to get on board. The Participator (majority rule) encourages the group members to participate, offers guidance but retains final say over the decision making. They spend time building consensus amongst the group, using that consensus to drive the direction. While the delegator (let do) offers little or no guidance to the group and leaves decision making up the group members. Kurt Lewin studied the three styles of leadership and discovered that members of an authoritarian leadership are the most productive, though members of participator leaders contributions while less productive did produce higher quality output. While members of a delegator leader often lack motivation and have poorly defined roles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think my personal style is part authoritarian and part participator. Properly more authoritarian then participator but I think that is a result of my drive from being goal and outcome driven. Though I also recognise the need to be a participator and get people involved and owning what they are doing. I lean away from the delegator style mainly due to the fact I believe it is important for a leader to have the answers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reflecting on my current frustrations I boiled my frustration down to the meetings about meetings about meetings. Did I mention there are a lot of meetings. It seemed that everything was being done through committee, which appeared to be an ineffective use of time. So when I was listening to the Podcast the comments about Bob Hawke being a leader of consensus it rang some bells and I decided to do a little more reading on leadership styles. As I reflected more on it I realised that it was the lack of productive outcomes, outputs and an apparent poor utilisation of time. The group dynamics where lending themselves towards the delegator style, causing me to have an undefined role and tasks within the group. Making me increasingly frustrated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the name of balance and yin yang a good leader most be able apply all three styles and be able to identify when it is appropriate to use which style. They must be able to use the authoritative style when the group lacks knowledge, use the participative style when the group clearly understands their objectives and there roles in the task and use the delegative style when the members know more about the task at hand then they do. Participative leadership is said to be the most effective style of leadership though I think it can easily become a delegator style, the least effective, if the leader does not retain the final say over the decision making.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="management" /><category term="leadership" /><summary>The father of leadership is arguably the psychologist Kurt Lewin, who in 1939 proposed that there are 3 styles of leadership:


  The Authoritarian (Autocratic)
  The Participator (Democratic)
  The Delegator (Laissez-faire)


The authoritarian – rule by ones self – leader provides clear expectations for what needs to be done, when it should be completed and how to complete it. They provide vision and direction and then try to convince people to get on board. The Participator (majority rule) encourages the group members to participate, offers guidance but retains final say over the decision making. They spend time building consensus amongst the group, using that consensus to drive the direction. While the delegator (let do) offers little or no guidance to the group and leaves decision making up the group members. Kurt Lewin studied the three styles of leadership and discovered that members of an authoritarian leadership are the most productive, though members of participator leaders contributions while less productive did produce higher quality output. While members of a delegator leader often lack motivation and have poorly defined roles.

I think my personal style is part authoritarian and part participator. Properly more authoritarian then participator but I think that is a result of my drive from being goal and outcome driven. Though I also recognise the need to be a participator and get people involved and owning what they are doing. I lean away from the delegator style mainly due to the fact I believe it is important for a leader to have the answers.

Reflecting on my current frustrations I boiled my frustration down to the meetings about meetings about meetings. Did I mention there are a lot of meetings. It seemed that everything was being done through committee, which appeared to be an ineffective use of time. So when I was listening to the Podcast the comments about Bob Hawke being a leader of consensus it rang some bells and I decided to do a little more reading on leadership styles. As I reflected more on it I realised that it was the lack of productive outcomes, outputs and an apparent poor utilisation of time. The group dynamics where lending themselves towards the delegator style, causing me to have an undefined role and tasks within the group. Making me increasingly frustrated.

In the name of balance and yin yang a good leader most be able apply all three styles and be able to identify when it is appropriate to use which style. They must be able to use the authoritative style when the group lacks knowledge, use the participative style when the group clearly understands their objectives and there roles in the task and use the delegative style when the members know more about the task at hand then they do. Participative leadership is said to be the most effective style of leadership though I think it can easily become a delegator style, the least effective, if the leader does not retain the final say over the decision making.</summary></entry><entry><title>A Journey With Cancer</title><link href="https://ianteda.com/creativity/a-journey-with-cancer.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Journey With Cancer" /><published>2016-01-29T00:00:00+11:00</published><updated>2016-01-29T00:00:00+11:00</updated><id>https://ianteda.com/creativity/a-journey-with-cancer</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ianteda.com/creativity/a-journey-with-cancer.html">&lt;p&gt;I would like to acknowledge and thank all those that helped and supported my dad on his final journey and the Teda family after his passing. Your love is very much appreciated and heartfelt. Thank You.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reflecting on what I saw in my dad, a lot of words, character traits come to mind:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A husband&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A father&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A family man&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A lover&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A wise man&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A man with integrity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shined the light of life&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Had a spirit of adventure&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The desire to explore&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A determination&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A film maker&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A hard worker&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An enjoyment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Holidays&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Great courage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dignity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Acceptance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Skilled hands&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Finished the race&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It still isn’t easy to talk about my dad’s final journey and it is still a little fresh, but I think his journey with cancer illustrates well his character. The person that he was and the type of character that he was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His journey with cancer, I think can best be described as a mysterious journey of unknown certainty. Where the outcome is certain (death) but the destiny a mystery (life after death) and the path unknown (everyone is different). My dad walked this journey with great courage and strength. He was joined on this path by the enduring and never ending lover of his wife, companion and best friend. Who demonstrated great courage and strength of her own. I am extremely proud of the way both my parents carried themselves during this time. With great dignity and care for each other. Dads first concern, when diagnosed was for the well being of his family. That his wife will be taken care of and that his family will be ok.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early on during his journey as we sat around at home I asked him “What he wanted to be remembered for”. His answer “That he gave to his kids, to his family the most precious thing anyone can give, his time”. Many of the family photos found in our photo albums were taken during family holidays. This is a testament to just that, time spent with his family. I don’t think I have ever met anyone that was taken on as many family holidays as his children were. While Laura and I where honeymooning in Fiji, enjoying the weather and warm water Laura asked me “if this is the best holiday ever?” My answer, “hmmm, maybe not as good as Blowering dam”. Our family holidays are for me by fare my fondest childhood memories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past I have been accused of being stubborn and told “it is ok to ask for help”. This I think is one character trait I can say I shared with dad. Other words for stubborn could also be hard working, determined or finisher. All through his journey with cancer Dad was up early showering and shaving himself. He never complained about the situation he found himself in, why me. He always did for himself that what he could. He never gave up hope, sure he wavered but he always tried.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You hear people saying “I’m not going to be like my parents”, “I’m never going to do this like my parents did”. For me my hope and prayer is that I can one day be as great a man, as great a father and husband that my dad was. As children we don’t always see the things that our parents do for us, I certainly didn’t. We just expect them to do, situation normal. However with passing of time and as I saw the way my friends interacted with their children I have began to see. To see just how much dad and just how much mum did for their children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last week of his life was tough for all involved, but was a something we all went through together and choose to be part of because of our love. During this time as I sat there with dad listening to the familiar sounds of the birds outside, the sound of the wind in the trees and the unique sounds found in every house I understood why he wanted to undertake the final part of his journey at home. At home surrounded by the love of his family and in the house that he put some much of time, so much his love into. His skill full hands can be seen throughout the house. In the TV cabinet he built, in the bathroom he built, in the kitchen he built, the garage he built, the garden tendered to, everywhere. He put all that he was into his house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sat there on his final day watching his irregular and labored breathing emotionally torn. As one breath was being expelled I was saying my good byes, letting him go, wanting his pain to be over for dad to find his peace. On the other breath I was willing him to keep breathing. I’m not ready, come on breath dam it! In the end the choice is not mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He lives on in all of those he touched, in the valves he taught his children, the receding hair line he passed onto his sons, the love he showed his wife and the things that he made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you all for your prayers, thoughts and gifts during this journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;God bless.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="creativity" /><category term="life" /><summary>I would like to acknowledge and thank all those that helped and supported my dad on his final journey and the Teda family after his passing. Your love is very much appreciated and heartfelt. Thank You.

Reflecting on what I saw in my dad, a lot of words, character traits come to mind:


  A husband
  A father
  A family man
  A lover
  A wise man
  A man with integrity
  Shined the light of life
  Had a spirit of adventure
  The desire to explore
  A determination
  A film maker
  A hard worker
  An enjoyment
  Holidays
  Great courage
  Dignity
  Acceptance
  Skilled hands
  Finished the race


It still isn’t easy to talk about my dad’s final journey and it is still a little fresh, but I think his journey with cancer illustrates well his character. The person that he was and the type of character that he was.

His journey with cancer, I think can best be described as a mysterious journey of unknown certainty. Where the outcome is certain (death) but the destiny a mystery (life after death) and the path unknown (everyone is different). My dad walked this journey with great courage and strength. He was joined on this path by the enduring and never ending lover of his wife, companion and best friend. Who demonstrated great courage and strength of her own. I am extremely proud of the way both my parents carried themselves during this time. With great dignity and care for each other. Dads first concern, when diagnosed was for the well being of his family. That his wife will be taken care of and that his family will be ok.

Early on during his journey as we sat around at home I asked him “What he wanted to be remembered for”. His answer “That he gave to his kids, to his family the most precious thing anyone can give, his time”. Many of the family photos found in our photo albums were taken during family holidays. This is a testament to just that, time spent with his family. I don’t think I have ever met anyone that was taken on as many family holidays as his children were. While Laura and I where honeymooning in Fiji, enjoying the weather and warm water Laura asked me “if this is the best holiday ever?” My answer, “hmmm, maybe not as good as Blowering dam”. Our family holidays are for me by fare my fondest childhood memories.

In the past I have been accused of being stubborn and told “it is ok to ask for help”. This I think is one character trait I can say I shared with dad. Other words for stubborn could also be hard working, determined or finisher. All through his journey with cancer Dad was up early showering and shaving himself. He never complained about the situation he found himself in, why me. He always did for himself that what he could. He never gave up hope, sure he wavered but he always tried.

You hear people saying “I’m not going to be like my parents”, “I’m never going to do this like my parents did”. For me my hope and prayer is that I can one day be as great a man, as great a father and husband that my dad was. As children we don’t always see the things that our parents do for us, I certainly didn’t. We just expect them to do, situation normal. However with passing of time and as I saw the way my friends interacted with their children I have began to see. To see just how much dad and just how much mum did for their children.

The last week of his life was tough for all involved, but was a something we all went through together and choose to be part of because of our love. During this time as I sat there with dad listening to the familiar sounds of the birds outside, the sound of the wind in the trees and the unique sounds found in every house I understood why he wanted to undertake the final part of his journey at home. At home surrounded by the love of his family and in the house that he put some much of time, so much his love into. His skill full hands can be seen throughout the house. In the TV cabinet he built, in the bathroom he built, in the kitchen he built, the garage he built, the garden tendered to, everywhere. He put all that he was into his house.

I sat there on his final day watching his irregular and labored breathing emotionally torn. As one breath was being expelled I was saying my good byes, letting him go, wanting his pain to be over for dad to find his peace. On the other breath I was willing him to keep breathing. I’m not ready, come on breath dam it! In the end the choice is not mine.

He lives on in all of those he touched, in the valves he taught his children, the receding hair line he passed onto his sons, the love he showed his wife and the things that he made.

Thank you all for your prayers, thoughts and gifts during this journey.

God bless.</summary></entry><entry><title>A Letter to my Sons</title><link href="https://ianteda.com/creativity/a-letter-to-sons.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Letter to my Sons" /><published>2016-01-29T00:00:00+11:00</published><updated>2016-01-29T00:00:00+11:00</updated><id>https://ianteda.com/creativity/a-letter-to-sons</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ianteda.com/creativity/a-letter-to-sons.html">&lt;p&gt;Live, love, be generous, show respect and give thanks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Know who you are and remember were you came from, but always look forward to were you are going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time is the most valuable thing you have, as death comes to us all. So spend your time wisely and without regrets. Make peace with God, yourself, your family and your friends so that when the day comes for you to face the great divide, you face it without the fear of death in your heart and without regrets. That your journey across will be one of ease and satisfaction of a life lived with only mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Show respect to others and demand they respect you. Abuse no one and nothing because abuse turns the wise to fools and robs the spirit of its vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Give thanks for what you have and for the joy of life. If you see no reason to give thanks, the fault lies only in yourself.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="creativity" /><category term="Philosophy" /><summary>Live, love, be generous, show respect and give thanks.

Know who you are and remember were you came from, but always look forward to were you are going.

Time is the most valuable thing you have, as death comes to us all. So spend your time wisely and without regrets. Make peace with God, yourself, your family and your friends so that when the day comes for you to face the great divide, you face it without the fear of death in your heart and without regrets. That your journey across will be one of ease and satisfaction of a life lived with only mistakes.

Show respect to others and demand they respect you. Abuse no one and nothing because abuse turns the wise to fools and robs the spirit of its vision.

Give thanks for what you have and for the joy of life. If you see no reason to give thanks, the fault lies only in yourself.</summary></entry><entry><title>Welcome to ianteda.com</title><link href="https://ianteda.com/management/ianteda-com.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to ianteda.com" /><published>2016-01-21T00:00:00+11:00</published><updated>2016-01-21T00:00:00+11:00</updated><id>https://ianteda.com/management/ianteda-com</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ianteda.com/management/ianteda-com.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/head-shot.png&quot; alt=&quot;Ian Teda photo&quot; title=&quot;Optional Title&quot; class=&quot;img-circle&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello and thank you for visiting &lt;a href=&quot;ianteda.com&quot;&gt;ianteda.com&lt;/a&gt;, my little corner of the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I created &lt;a href=&quot;ianteda.com&quot;&gt;ianteda.com&lt;/a&gt; with the desire to be useful by providing content around ideas, thoughts and projects I am learning and working on. Second to being useful, I wanted to build and manage my professional image, brand and authority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of being useful came from &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.dilbert.com/post/130338537981/the-moist-robot-ethical-code&quot;&gt;Scott Adams&lt;/a&gt; the creator of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://dilbert.com&quot;&gt;Dilbert Cartoons&lt;/a&gt;. The answer to the ultimate question of Life, the Universe, and Everything is not &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=42&quot;&gt;42&lt;/a&gt; but “Be Useful”. Need a business idea? How can you be useful. What should I do in life? Be useful. How can I get people to like me? Be useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can I be useful? By providing content around ideas, thoughts and projects, putting a URL to it ( thanks &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hanselman.com/blog/YourWordsAreWasted.aspx&quot;&gt;Scott Hanselman&lt;/a&gt;) and sharing. It comes with the added bonuses of helping build a brand, authority, practice my writing and help develop ideas through the articulation of writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To find out more about me check out the &lt;a href=&quot;/about.html&quot;&gt;About&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To find out what I am currently working on check out the &lt;a href=&quot;/now.html&quot;&gt;Now&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="management" /><category term="Business" /><category term="Professional" /><summary>Hello and thank you for visiting ianteda.com, my little corner of the Internet.

I created ianteda.com with the desire to be useful by providing content around ideas, thoughts and projects I am learning and working on. Second to being useful, I wanted to build and manage my professional image, brand and authority.

The concept of being useful came from Scott Adams the creator of the Dilbert Cartoons. The answer to the ultimate question of Life, the Universe, and Everything is not 42 but “Be Useful”. Need a business idea? How can you be useful. What should I do in life? Be useful. How can I get people to like me? Be useful.

How can I be useful? By providing content around ideas, thoughts and projects, putting a URL to it ( thanks Scott Hanselman) and sharing. It comes with the added bonuses of helping build a brand, authority, practice my writing and help develop ideas through the articulation of writing.

To find out more about me check out the About

To find out what I am currently working on check out the Now</summary></entry><entry><title>Be Bold &amp;amp; Make Mistakes</title><link href="https://ianteda.com/creativity/bold-mistakes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Be Bold &amp; Make Mistakes" /><published>2016-01-19T00:00:00+11:00</published><updated>2016-01-19T00:00:00+11:00</updated><id>https://ianteda.com/creativity/bold-mistakes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ianteda.com/creativity/bold-mistakes.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;All courses of action are risky, so prudence is not in avoiding danger (it’s impossible), but calculating risk and acting decisively. Make mistakes of ambition and not mistakes of sloth. Develop the strength to do bold things, not the strength to suffer.
&lt;cite&gt;– Chapter III: Of Mixed Princedoms&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is risk with all things in life. It cannot be avoided so do not let the possibility of failure prevent action. An indecision is still a decision. Move forward knowing that the decision you made was the right one, based on the knowledge you had at the time. Whether or not it turns out to be right is besides the point, considered action is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Becoming successful requires risk and with risk comes mistakes. It is through these mistakes that we learn and grow. We can try and avoid risk but in the end we will make mistakes. However, there are mistakes of sloth (mistakes) and mistakes of ambition. Mistake of sloth lead to missed opportunity and regret. While, for the most part mistakes of ambition will be forgiven because they come from good intentions. Mistakes of sloth are not so easily forgiven and often it is ourselves that are the last to forget, because of our regret.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Success for the most part is subjective, but what ever your measure may be it still requires action. It is comfortable to stay on the path of least resistance, because it is well walked. But be bold and walk the road less traveled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[^] &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0486272745/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0486272745&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=iate-20&amp;amp;linkId=XF6OTL2R2FAENV6H&quot;&gt;The Prince&lt;/a&gt; by Niccolò Machiavelli. Written in the 16th century, it is about acquiring power and maintaining it (pre democracy).&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="creativity" /><category term="Philosophy" /><summary>All courses of action are risky, so prudence is not in avoiding danger (it’s impossible), but calculating risk and acting decisively. Make mistakes of ambition and not mistakes of sloth. Develop the strength to do bold things, not the strength to suffer.
– Chapter III: Of Mixed Princedoms


There is risk with all things in life. It cannot be avoided so do not let the possibility of failure prevent action. An indecision is still a decision. Move forward knowing that the decision you made was the right one, based on the knowledge you had at the time. Whether or not it turns out to be right is besides the point, considered action is.

Becoming successful requires risk and with risk comes mistakes. It is through these mistakes that we learn and grow. We can try and avoid risk but in the end we will make mistakes. However, there are mistakes of sloth (mistakes) and mistakes of ambition. Mistake of sloth lead to missed opportunity and regret. While, for the most part mistakes of ambition will be forgiven because they come from good intentions. Mistakes of sloth are not so easily forgiven and often it is ourselves that are the last to forget, because of our regret.

Success for the most part is subjective, but what ever your measure may be it still requires action. It is comfortable to stay on the path of least resistance, because it is well walked. But be bold and walk the road less traveled.

[^] The Prince by Niccolò Machiavelli. Written in the 16th century, it is about acquiring power and maintaining it (pre democracy).</summary></entry></feed>
