<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.4.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://ianteda.com/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://ianteda.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-05-27T09:00:18+10:00</updated><id>https://ianteda.com/</id><title type="html">Ian Teda</title><subtitle>Husband, Father, Engineer, Explorer &amp; Creator</subtitle><author><name>Ian Teda</name><email>ian@teda.id.au</email></author><entry><title type="html">Rule 11 - Finding Time</title><link href="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-11-finding-time.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rule 11 - Finding Time" /><published>2017-05-18T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-05-18T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-11-finding-time</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-11-finding-time.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Time is the measurer of all things, but is itself immeasurable, and the grand discloser of all things, but is itself undisclosed. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt; - Charles Caleb Colton&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It all boils down to time. After all, money is just the value we place on time. It makes sense then, that the most valuable gift you can give is your time. Because, we don’t know how much we have, we cannot make more of it and once it has turned into yesterday we cannot get it back. When we are young it seems to go on for ever and yet our time maybe up tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you love life, don’t waste time, for time is what life is made up of. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;- Bruce Lee&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If time is the most valuable thing we have, then it makes sense to maximise our return. How? Through the routine and discipline of prioritising our demands, executing on our priorities, measuring our output and adapting as needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are not the master of your time, then time will be the master of you - i.e. you will not have any. Routine is about setting up habits, rituals and behaviours to optimise your time. It is the discipline in these routines that gives you freedom, the freedom to choose what we do with our time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Time is free, but its priceless. You can’t own it, but you can use it. You can’t keep it, but you can spend it. Once you’ve lost it, you can never get it back. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;- Harvey Mackay&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step in prioritising your time is to apply the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pareto_principle&quot;&gt;Pareto Principle&lt;/a&gt;. Research has shown that
80% of your output will typically comes from 20% of your input. With that in mind you need to figure out what your 20% input is and delegate as much of the remainder of your input as possible. Leaving you time to improve the quality of your 80% output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A man who dares to waste one hour of time has not discovered the value of life. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;- Charles Darwin&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favourite tool to manage my time (priorities) is the &lt;a href=&quot;http://bulletjournal.com/&quot;&gt;bullet journal&lt;/a&gt;. To quote the Bullet Journal website, it is &lt;em&gt;“the analog system for the digital age. The Bullet Journal is a customizable and forgiving organization system. It can be your to-do list, sketchbook, notebook, and diary, but most likely, it will be all of the above. It will teach you to do more with less.”&lt;/em&gt; I would call myself a digital kind of person, but there is something about writing things down and the customisable nature of paper that has won me over. I have been using it for two years now and think it is the best tool for solidifying thoughts, remembering tasks, prioritising demands and tracking output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The strongest of all warriors are these two — Time and Patience. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;- Leo Tolstoy&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is safe to say that you cannot make a baby with nine women in one month. That sometimes things take, what they take and putting more resources on it will not accelerate time. So you need to deploy a little patience, with some determination thrown in. You can always throw an extra scraper fleet info it, but a D11 can only do so many pushes an hour. Meaning you can physically only fit so many scrapers into the one area and a D11 can only push so many 651s per hour. This is particularly true when it comes to changing groups of people, changing cultural habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Yesterday is gone. Tomorrow has not yet come. We have only today. Let us begin. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;- Mother Teresa&lt;cite&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Question:&lt;/em&gt; How do you find time?
&lt;em&gt;Answer:&lt;/em&gt; Take control of your time, to find time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Time is, time was, but time shall be no more. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;- James Joyce&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Ian Teda</name><email>ian@teda.id.au</email></author><category term="engineering" /><category term="construction" /><category term="rule-book" /><summary type="html">Time is the measurer of all things, but is itself immeasurable, and the grand discloser of all things, but is itself undisclosed. - Charles Caleb Colton It all boils down to time. After all, money is just the value we place on time. It makes sense then, that the most valuable gift you can give is your time. Because, we don’t know how much we have, we cannot make more of it and once it has turned into yesterday we cannot get it back. When we are young it seems to go on for ever and yet our time maybe up tomorrow. If you love life, don’t waste time, for time is what life is made up of. - Bruce Lee If time is the most valuable thing we have, then it makes sense to maximise our return. How? Through the routine and discipline of prioritising our demands, executing on our priorities, measuring our output and adapting as needed. If you are not the master of your time, then time will be the master of you - i.e. you will not have any. Routine is about setting up habits, rituals and behaviours to optimise your time. It is the discipline in these routines that gives you freedom, the freedom to choose what we do with our time. Time is free, but its priceless. You can’t own it, but you can use it. You can’t keep it, but you can spend it. Once you’ve lost it, you can never get it back. - Harvey Mackay The first step in prioritising your time is to apply the Pareto Principle. Research has shown that 80% of your output will typically comes from 20% of your input. With that in mind you need to figure out what your 20% input is and delegate as much of the remainder of your input as possible. Leaving you time to improve the quality of your 80% output. A man who dares to waste one hour of time has not discovered the value of life. - Charles Darwin My favourite tool to manage my time (priorities) is the bullet journal. To quote the Bullet Journal website, it is “the analog system for the digital age. The Bullet Journal is a customizable and forgiving organization system. It can be your to-do list, sketchbook, notebook, and diary, but most likely, it will be all of the above. It will teach you to do more with less.” I would call myself a digital kind of person, but there is something about writing things down and the customisable nature of paper that has won me over. I have been using it for two years now and think it is the best tool for solidifying thoughts, remembering tasks, prioritising demands and tracking output. The strongest of all warriors are these two — Time and Patience. - Leo Tolstoy It is safe to say that you cannot make a baby with nine women in one month. That sometimes things take, what they take and putting more resources on it will not accelerate time. So you need to deploy a little patience, with some determination thrown in. You can always throw an extra scraper fleet info it, but a D11 can only do so many pushes an hour. Meaning you can physically only fit so many scrapers into the one area and a D11 can only push so many 651s per hour. This is particularly true when it comes to changing groups of people, changing cultural habits. Yesterday is gone. Tomorrow has not yet come. We have only today. Let us begin. - Mother Teresa Question: How do you find time? Answer: Take control of your time, to find time. Time is, time was, but time shall be no more. - James Joyce</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rule 10 - Pop quiz, what is the number?</title><link href="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-10-pop-quiz.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rule 10 - Pop quiz, what is the number?" /><published>2017-05-18T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-05-18T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-10-pop-quiz</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-10-pop-quiz.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You don’t know, what you don’t know.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;- Unknown&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Never have truer words been spoken. It is always the unknown unknowns that get you. Because they blind side you when you are looking the other way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What gets measured gets managed.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;- Peter Drucker&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want people to focus on something, ask them to measure it. And pop quiz them each day about what the number is. The pop quiz will help:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Force them to understand what is going on&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:rule3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:rule3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Give you a level of confidence they have the situation under control. If from day to day they know how the number has changed and why;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reinforce that this is important to you;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Allow you adapt sooner to changes. With the level of detail or how often you measure being relative to the complexity and size;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Measurement is fabulous. Unless you are busy measuring what is easy to measure as opposed to what’s important.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;  - Seth Godin&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worried about not meeting program: measure how many m3 of concrete have gone in, tonnes of reinforcement or dollars spent to date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worried about the budget: measure man hours, plant hours or wastage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One accurate measurement, is worth a thousand expert opinions.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;- Unknown&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best tool I have found for measuring on construction projects is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earned_value_management&quot;&gt;Earn Value Analysis (EVA)&lt;/a&gt;. It allows you to measure scope, time and costs against planned work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you don’t know how your are performing relative to the plan, how do you know when you are off track and need correction?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt; - Personal&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-book.html&quot;&gt;Engineering Rule Book&lt;/a&gt; for the other rules.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:rule3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-3-dont-give-me-surprises.html&quot;&gt;Rule 3 - Give me good news, give bad news. Just don’t give me surprises&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:rule3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Ian Teda</name><email>ian@teda.id.au</email></author><category term="engineering" /><category term="construction" /><category term="rule-book" /><summary type="html">You don’t know, what you don’t know.- Unknown Never have truer words been spoken. It is always the unknown unknowns that get you. Because they blind side you when you are looking the other way. What gets measured gets managed.- Peter Drucker If you want people to focus on something, ask them to measure it. And pop quiz them each day about what the number is. The pop quiz will help: Force them to understand what is going on1; Give you a level of confidence they have the situation under control. If from day to day they know how the number has changed and why; Reinforce that this is important to you; Allow you adapt sooner to changes. With the level of detail or how often you measure being relative to the complexity and size; Measurement is fabulous. Unless you are busy measuring what is easy to measure as opposed to what’s important. - Seth Godin Worried about not meeting program: measure how many m3 of concrete have gone in, tonnes of reinforcement or dollars spent to date. Worried about the budget: measure man hours, plant hours or wastage. One accurate measurement, is worth a thousand expert opinions.- Unknown The best tool I have found for measuring on construction projects is Earn Value Analysis (EVA). It allows you to measure scope, time and costs against planned work. If you don’t know how your are performing relative to the plan, how do you know when you are off track and need correction? - Personal Check out the Engineering Rule Book for the other rules. Rule 3 - Give me good news, give bad news. Just don’t give me surprises&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8617;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rule 9 - Always start with the end in mind.</title><link href="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-9-always-start-with-the-end-in-mind.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rule 9 - Always start with the end in mind." /><published>2017-05-10T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-05-10T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-9-always-start-with-the-end-in-mind</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-9-always-start-with-the-end-in-mind.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I can’t change the direction of the wind, but I can adjust my sails to always reach my destination. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;– Jimmy Dean&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Always start with the end in mind. What is the ideal outcome? What is your destination? And then breakdown the journey into manageable pieces, reverse engineering the path to get there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t have a destination, you don’t have direction. And if you don’t have direction you are lost, going around and around in circles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By prevailing over all obstacles and distractions, one may unfailingly arrive at his chosen goal or destination. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;– Christopher Columbus&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The path isn’t always clear, because the path is not always well traveled. But with an end in mind, a good internal compass and a belief in self you can reach your destination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good internal compass is about optimism. The optimism that the destination is achievable, even when the path isn’t clear. But a good internal compass is not just about optimism, it is also about having enough self awareness to know when a correction is needed. To know when you have strayed off course and need to get back on the path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The path less traveled can be dangerous, it is uncharted and filled with traps. And when pioneering, when innovating often you will need to be the first to taste the berries and hope they are not poisonous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To become ‘unique,’ the challenge is to fight the hardest battle which anyone can imagine until you reach your destination. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;– A. P. J. Abdul Kalam&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-book.html&quot;&gt;Engineering Rule Book&lt;/a&gt; for the other rules.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ian Teda</name><email>ian@teda.id.au</email></author><category term="engineering" /><category term="construction" /><category term="rule-book" /><summary type="html">I can’t change the direction of the wind, but I can adjust my sails to always reach my destination. – Jimmy Dean Always start with the end in mind. What is the ideal outcome? What is your destination? And then breakdown the journey into manageable pieces, reverse engineering the path to get there. If you don’t have a destination, you don’t have direction. And if you don’t have direction you are lost, going around and around in circles. By prevailing over all obstacles and distractions, one may unfailingly arrive at his chosen goal or destination. – Christopher Columbus The path isn’t always clear, because the path is not always well traveled. But with an end in mind, a good internal compass and a belief in self you can reach your destination. A good internal compass is about optimism. The optimism that the destination is achievable, even when the path isn’t clear. But a good internal compass is not just about optimism, it is also about having enough self awareness to know when a correction is needed. To know when you have strayed off course and need to get back on the path. The path less traveled can be dangerous, it is uncharted and filled with traps. And when pioneering, when innovating often you will need to be the first to taste the berries and hope they are not poisonous. To become ‘unique,’ the challenge is to fight the hardest battle which anyone can imagine until you reach your destination. – A. P. J. Abdul Kalam Check out the Engineering Rule Book for the other rules.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rule 8 - Keep one eye open and your ear to the ground.</title><link href="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-8-eye-and-ear.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rule 8 - Keep one eye open and your ear to the ground." /><published>2017-05-03T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-05-03T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-8-eye-and-ear</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-8-eye-and-ear.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Blinding ignorance does mislead us. O! Wretched mortals, open your eyes! &lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;- Leonardo da Vinci&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is easy to focus on your work and for your work to become your world. But it is equally important to keep the bigger picture in mind and maintain perspective. To learn the context of where your work fits into the bigger machine, what external forces could effect your work and how you might be able to help others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, take the long slow way around site. Keeping one eye open, observing what others are doing. And your ear to the ground, listening to what others are saying in meetings and in conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By doing this you are able to answer more questions, know the right person to ask your question and where to find that stock N16 bar when you under order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Rule 8 - Keep One Eye Open and Your Ear to the Ground&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-book.html&quot;&gt;Engineering Rule Book&lt;/a&gt; for the other rules.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ian Teda</name><email>ian@teda.id.au</email></author><category term="engineering" /><category term="construction" /><category term="rule-book" /><summary type="html">Blinding ignorance does mislead us. O! Wretched mortals, open your eyes! - Leonardo da Vinci It is easy to focus on your work and for your work to become your world. But it is equally important to keep the bigger picture in mind and maintain perspective. To learn the context of where your work fits into the bigger machine, what external forces could effect your work and how you might be able to help others. With that in mind, take the long slow way around site. Keeping one eye open, observing what others are doing. And your ear to the ground, listening to what others are saying in meetings and in conversation. By doing this you are able to answer more questions, know the right person to ask your question and where to find that stock N16 bar when you under order. Rule 8 - Keep One Eye Open and Your Ear to the Ground Check out the Engineering Rule Book for the other rules.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rule 7 - Do not walk past it.</title><link href="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-7-do-not-walk-past-it.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rule 7 - Do not walk past it." /><published>2017-04-25T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-04-25T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-7-do-not-walk-past-it</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-7-do-not-walk-past-it.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The standard you walk past, is the standard you accept. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt; - David Morrison&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be it a safety concern, poor workmanship or bad behaviour if you close your eyes and walk past it then you are accepting it. You are saying that you are not concerned and feel free to keep doing it without correction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To live by this rule means difficult conversations, extra work and extra responsibility. Not everyone goes looking for or wants these things. But ignoring this rule leads to regret, disappointment and mediocrity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Big problems can often be avoid by addressing small problems that come past you. So don’t ignore the small problems, by walking past them. Instead get out in front of them and avoid the big ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-book.html&quot;&gt;Engineering Rule Book&lt;/a&gt; for the other rules.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ian Teda</name><email>ian@teda.id.au</email></author><category term="engineering" /><category term="construction" /><category term="rule-book" /><summary type="html">The standard you walk past, is the standard you accept. - David Morrison Be it a safety concern, poor workmanship or bad behaviour if you close your eyes and walk past it then you are accepting it. You are saying that you are not concerned and feel free to keep doing it without correction. To live by this rule means difficult conversations, extra work and extra responsibility. Not everyone goes looking for or wants these things. But ignoring this rule leads to regret, disappointment and mediocrity. Big problems can often be avoid by addressing small problems that come past you. So don’t ignore the small problems, by walking past them. Instead get out in front of them and avoid the big ones. Check out the Engineering Rule Book for the other rules.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rule 6 - Respect the 6 Ps.</title><link href="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-6-the-6-ps.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rule 6 - Respect the 6 Ps." /><published>2017-04-20T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-04-20T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-6-the-6-ps</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-6-the-6-ps.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The 6 Ps: Prior Planning Prevents Piss Poor Performance. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt; - U.S. Army&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Respect the 6 Ps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prior&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Planning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prevents&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Piss&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Poor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Performance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1---prior&quot;&gt;1 - Prior&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Give me six hours to chop down a tree and I will spend the first four sharpening the axe. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt; - Abraham Lincoln&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t leave your planning to the last moment. Insteed, dive into the detail early to make sure a lack of planning doesn’t become somebody else’s priority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2---planning&quot;&gt;2 - Planning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A goal without a plan is just a wish!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pictures! There is a reason why we build of drawings. And planning should be no different. Make drawings, sketches and slides to convey your message, the mental picture of how it is going to be built. Your vision if you would.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3---prevents&quot;&gt;3 - Prevents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A plan that everyone dislikes for different reasons is a success. A plan everyone dislikes for the same reason is a failure. And a plan that everyone likes for the same reason is an act of God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ensure understanding of your vision by asking for feedback. And be humble enough to accept criticsm and adapt your plan as needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4---piss&quot;&gt;4 - Piss&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There are two kinds of failures: those who thought and never did, and those who did and never thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consult grey haired people. This isn’t the first time, so learn from other peoples mistakes and avoid mistakes of the past. Search out common school boy errors and plan around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5---poor&quot;&gt;5 - Poor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Those who fail to plan, plans to fail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You never really learn something until you have to teach it. So the best way to understand howto build something is to try and explain it to someone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6---performance&quot;&gt;6 - Performance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Poor planning or poor execution of plans is simply to let some force other than reason shape reality. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt; - Robert McNamara&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can spend your time putting out fires, or you can spent your time planning and adapting. If you spend all your time putting out fires, then for the most part your destiny is being set by other forces outside your control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-book.html&quot;&gt;Engineering Rule Book&lt;/a&gt; for the other rules.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ian Teda</name><email>ian@teda.id.au</email></author><category term="engineering" /><category term="construction" /><category term="rule-book" /><summary type="html">The 6 Ps: Prior Planning Prevents Piss Poor Performance. - U.S. Army Respect the 6 Ps: Prior Planning Prevents Piss Poor Performance 1 - Prior Give me six hours to chop down a tree and I will spend the first four sharpening the axe. - Abraham Lincoln Don’t leave your planning to the last moment. Insteed, dive into the detail early to make sure a lack of planning doesn’t become somebody else’s priority. 2 - Planning A goal without a plan is just a wish! Pictures! There is a reason why we build of drawings. And planning should be no different. Make drawings, sketches and slides to convey your message, the mental picture of how it is going to be built. Your vision if you would. 3 - Prevents A plan that everyone dislikes for different reasons is a success. A plan everyone dislikes for the same reason is a failure. And a plan that everyone likes for the same reason is an act of God. Ensure understanding of your vision by asking for feedback. And be humble enough to accept criticsm and adapt your plan as needed. 4 - Piss There are two kinds of failures: those who thought and never did, and those who did and never thought. Consult grey haired people. This isn’t the first time, so learn from other peoples mistakes and avoid mistakes of the past. Search out common school boy errors and plan around. 5 - Poor Those who fail to plan, plans to fail. You never really learn something until you have to teach it. So the best way to understand howto build something is to try and explain it to someone else. 6 - Performance Poor planning or poor execution of plans is simply to let some force other than reason shape reality. - Robert McNamara You can spend your time putting out fires, or you can spent your time planning and adapting. If you spend all your time putting out fires, then for the most part your destiny is being set by other forces outside your control. Check out the Engineering Rule Book for the other rules.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rule 5 - The early bird catches the worm, and enjoys the fruits of its labor.</title><link href="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-5-start-early.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rule 5 - The early bird catches the worm, and enjoys the fruits of its labor." /><published>2017-04-14T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-04-14T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-5-start-early</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-5-start-early.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The early bird catches the worm.
&lt;cite&gt; - William Camden&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Always try to start work early because it demonstrates that you want your job and you want to be there. Most things can be taught, enthusiasim and desire, for the most part, cannot be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting to work early gives you the oppurtunity to set the destiny of construction for the day. Otherwise you will be chasing your tail all day, trying to get construction moving in the direction you want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last reason is about respect. Don’t ask people to do things you wouldn’t do yourself. Your formen and workers are starting early, so should you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Fruits of one’s labor(s): the results of one’s work. We displayed the fruits of our labor at the county fair. What have you accomplished? Where is the fruit of your labors?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Construction work demands a lot of hours from you. Early mornings, late evenings, weekends and night shifts. But with those hours comes the satisfaction of seeing things get built. Creating something from nothing. Giving birth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slowly, little by little the project gets built. Untill finally it is born and you get to say “I had a part in building that”. That this town has better water, sewer, safer roads, better infrastructure because of the hours I put in. That during the hard times, and all projects have them, that there is a light at the end of the tunnel. An end and it is something you can tell your kids about. You get to see the fruits of your labour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-book.html&quot;&gt;Engineering Rule Book&lt;/a&gt; for the other rules.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ian Teda</name><email>ian@teda.id.au</email></author><category term="engineering" /><category term="construction" /><category term="rule-book" /><summary type="html">The early bird catches the worm. - William Camden Always try to start work early because it demonstrates that you want your job and you want to be there. Most things can be taught, enthusiasim and desire, for the most part, cannot be. Getting to work early gives you the oppurtunity to set the destiny of construction for the day. Otherwise you will be chasing your tail all day, trying to get construction moving in the direction you want. The last reason is about respect. Don’t ask people to do things you wouldn’t do yourself. Your formen and workers are starting early, so should you. Fruits of one’s labor(s): the results of one’s work. We displayed the fruits of our labor at the county fair. What have you accomplished? Where is the fruit of your labors? Construction work demands a lot of hours from you. Early mornings, late evenings, weekends and night shifts. But with those hours comes the satisfaction of seeing things get built. Creating something from nothing. Giving birth. Slowly, little by little the project gets built. Untill finally it is born and you get to say “I had a part in building that”. That this town has better water, sewer, safer roads, better infrastructure because of the hours I put in. That during the hard times, and all projects have them, that there is a light at the end of the tunnel. An end and it is something you can tell your kids about. You get to see the fruits of your labour. Check out the Engineering Rule Book for the other rules.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rule 4 - Relationships, say hello because success is largely a result of those around you.</title><link href="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-4-relationships-success.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rule 4 - Relationships, say hello because success is largely a result of those around you." /><published>2017-04-03T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-04-03T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-4-relationships-success</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-4-relationships-success.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You are the average of the five people you spend the most time with.
&lt;cite&gt;Jim Rohn&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From construction of the project to your career, success — however you measure it — is largely a result of the people around you. So make an effort to build relationships with everyone, from the project director to the members of the workforce. And the best way to build relationships is to say hello and make an effort to learn peoples name. But always be authentic in your relationships, because people will quickly see through you when your aim is to get something out of them. Your aim in any relationship should be about what you can do for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It does matter who you know, as it is often through the 2nd and 3rd levels of relationships that you find work opportunities, get promoted, grow outside your prejudices — you will always find people to reinforce your views when &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=Birds%20of%20a%20feather%20flock%20together&quot;&gt;birds of a feather flock together&lt;/a&gt; — or even meet your significant other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you want to make everyone happy, don’t be a leader - seal ice cream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-2-opposing-views.html&quot;&gt;rule 2&lt;/a&gt; here — the flip side, the other side of the coin — is that it isn’t a popularity contest and that you are not there to make friends. That often you will need to say no, making people upset. The easy answer is “Yes”, but don’t let yourself be pressured into a yes or avoid a hard truth because you don’t want to upset someone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Rule 4 - Relationships, say hello because success is largely a result of those around you&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-book.html&quot;&gt;Engineering Rule Book&lt;/a&gt; for the other rules.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ian Teda</name><email>ian@teda.id.au</email></author><category term="engineering" /><category term="construction" /><category term="rule-book" /><summary type="html">You are the average of the five people you spend the most time with. Jim Rohn From construction of the project to your career, success — however you measure it — is largely a result of the people around you. So make an effort to build relationships with everyone, from the project director to the members of the workforce. And the best way to build relationships is to say hello and make an effort to learn peoples name. But always be authentic in your relationships, because people will quickly see through you when your aim is to get something out of them. Your aim in any relationship should be about what you can do for them. It does matter who you know, as it is often through the 2nd and 3rd levels of relationships that you find work opportunities, get promoted, grow outside your prejudices — you will always find people to reinforce your views when birds of a feather flock together — or even meet your significant other. If you want to make everyone happy, don’t be a leader - seal ice cream. The rule 2 here — the flip side, the other side of the coin — is that it isn’t a popularity contest and that you are not there to make friends. That often you will need to say no, making people upset. The easy answer is “Yes”, but don’t let yourself be pressured into a yes or avoid a hard truth because you don’t want to upset someone. Rule 4 - Relationships, say hello because success is largely a result of those around you Check out the Engineering Rule Book for the other rules.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rule 3 - Give me good news, give bad news. Just don’t give me surprises.</title><link href="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-3-dont-give-me-surprises.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rule 3 - Give me good news, give bad news. Just don't give me surprises." /><published>2017-03-29T00:00:00+11:00</published><updated>2017-03-29T00:00:00+11:00</updated><id>https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-3-dont-give-me-surprises</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-3-dont-give-me-surprises.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Be in control of your destiny, by getting out in front of issues and avoiding suprises.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a manager, I want to know about the good news and the bad news. But don’t bring me surprises. Surprises indicate a lack of understanding and ownership of what you are responsible for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This rule is no better illustrated then in cost forecasting. If your quantities, rates and costs continually move around. And this comes as a surprise to you, then it is a good indicator that you are not in control of your work. And keep in mind that a surprise $1 million profit, 1 month out from closing a project is still a surprise. Was it by luck or good management that you made money? Were you in control? Should we trust you with more money? You should plan for the unknown unknowns, but be transparent about any contingency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things go wrong, everyone understands that. But there is a difference between bad news and surprises. Bad news is owning your mistakes, owning the unknowns and having a plan to mitigate any loses. Having a plan to stop the bleeding. Telling someone bad news and this is the plan, is a whole lot better then surprise we are losing money and I have no idea how much or how to mitigate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When bringing bad news about the costs, have an understanding why your quaities increased or why the rate changed. Know what the worst case is if thins are kept the sameπ – understanding the problem – and these are the changes we are making to bring the cost blow out back in – getting in front of the issue and controlling your destiny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Give me good news, give me bad news. Just don’t give me surprises. No one likes surprises. Make your mistakes ones of ambition, not sloth – &lt;a href=&quot;https://ianteda.com/creativity/the-bold-mistake-instruction.html&quot;&gt;The Bold Mistake Instruction&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Rule 3 - Give me good news, give bad news. Just don’t give me surprises&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-book.html&quot;&gt;Engineering Rule Book&lt;/a&gt; for the other rules.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ian Teda</name><email>ian@teda.id.au</email></author><category term="engineering" /><category term="construction" /><category term="rule-book" /><summary type="html">Be in control of your destiny, by getting out in front of issues and avoiding suprises. As a manager, I want to know about the good news and the bad news. But don’t bring me surprises. Surprises indicate a lack of understanding and ownership of what you are responsible for. This rule is no better illustrated then in cost forecasting. If your quantities, rates and costs continually move around. And this comes as a surprise to you, then it is a good indicator that you are not in control of your work. And keep in mind that a surprise $1 million profit, 1 month out from closing a project is still a surprise. Was it by luck or good management that you made money? Were you in control? Should we trust you with more money? You should plan for the unknown unknowns, but be transparent about any contingency. Things go wrong, everyone understands that. But there is a difference between bad news and surprises. Bad news is owning your mistakes, owning the unknowns and having a plan to mitigate any loses. Having a plan to stop the bleeding. Telling someone bad news and this is the plan, is a whole lot better then surprise we are losing money and I have no idea how much or how to mitigate it. When bringing bad news about the costs, have an understanding why your quaities increased or why the rate changed. Know what the worst case is if thins are kept the sameπ – understanding the problem – and these are the changes we are making to bring the cost blow out back in – getting in front of the issue and controlling your destiny. Give me good news, give me bad news. Just don’t give me surprises. No one likes surprises. Make your mistakes ones of ambition, not sloth – The Bold Mistake Instruction. Rule 3 - Give me good news, give bad news. Just don’t give me surprises Check out the Engineering Rule Book for the other rules.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rule 2 - When faced with opposing views, often the answer is both.</title><link href="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-2-opposing-views.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rule 2 - When faced with opposing views, often the answer is both." /><published>2017-03-25T00:00:00+11:00</published><updated>2017-03-25T00:00:00+11:00</updated><id>https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-2-opposing-views</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-2-opposing-views.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Much of life is a dichotomy, a contradiction and construction life is no different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When faced with what seem like mutually exclusive and opposing views, often the answer is both. Much of life is a dichotomy, a contradiction and construction life is no different. The skill comes in first realizing this, being comfortable with the contradictions and knowing how to find the balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rule 2, is a little bit of an abstract concept. But it is important as it adds context and framing to a lot of the other rules – i.e. a rule may be highlighting an extreme, but they doesn’t mean you should live at the extreme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The safest way to build something is not to build it at all. But that doesn’t get things built. The answer is you need to do both. It needs to be built and it needs to be built safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should I micro manage or macro manage? The answer is you should do both. There are times when you need to focus in on the detail to make sure things run smoothly, but you will get to a level of micro where the return on your time does not warrant the focus and you need to execute and step back into the macro so you can first see where you need adjust and then make the adjustment. The return is in the execution, but if you don’t but enough time into the detail the execution will fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should I be good cop or bad cop? The answer is both. You must be able to go to the extremes of being angry and being passive, and be able to recognise when and how to deploy each of them. But you cannot live life at the extreme of either. You need to be able to defend your ideas, but if you never change your mind people will not approach you with what could be the answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When faced with opposing views, often the answer is both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Rule 2 - When faced with opposing views, often the answer is both&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-book.html&quot;&gt;Engineering Rule Book&lt;/a&gt; for the other rules.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ian Teda</name><email>ian@teda.id.au</email></author><category term="engineering" /><category term="construction" /><category term="rule-book" /><summary type="html">Much of life is a dichotomy, a contradiction and construction life is no different. When faced with what seem like mutually exclusive and opposing views, often the answer is both. Much of life is a dichotomy, a contradiction and construction life is no different. The skill comes in first realizing this, being comfortable with the contradictions and knowing how to find the balance. Rule 2, is a little bit of an abstract concept. But it is important as it adds context and framing to a lot of the other rules – i.e. a rule may be highlighting an extreme, but they doesn’t mean you should live at the extreme. The safest way to build something is not to build it at all. But that doesn’t get things built. The answer is you need to do both. It needs to be built and it needs to be built safe. Should I micro manage or macro manage? The answer is you should do both. There are times when you need to focus in on the detail to make sure things run smoothly, but you will get to a level of micro where the return on your time does not warrant the focus and you need to execute and step back into the macro so you can first see where you need adjust and then make the adjustment. The return is in the execution, but if you don’t but enough time into the detail the execution will fail. Should I be good cop or bad cop? The answer is both. You must be able to go to the extremes of being angry and being passive, and be able to recognise when and how to deploy each of them. But you cannot live life at the extreme of either. You need to be able to defend your ideas, but if you never change your mind people will not approach you with what could be the answer. When faced with opposing views, often the answer is both. Rule 2 - When faced with opposing views, often the answer is both Check out the Engineering Rule Book for the other rules.</summary></entry></feed>