<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.4.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://ianteda.com/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://ianteda.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-07-03T20:07:43+10:00</updated><id>https://ianteda.com/</id><title type="html">Ian Teda</title><subtitle>Husband, Father, Engineer, Explorer &amp; Creator</subtitle><author><name>Ian Teda</name><email>ian@teda.id.au</email></author><entry><title type="html">Rule 15 - We Are All Paid To Think</title><link href="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-15-paid-to-think.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rule 15 - We Are All Paid To Think" /><published>2017-07-02T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-07-02T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-15-paid-to-think</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-15-paid-to-think.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Thinking is the hardest work there is, which is probably the reason why so few engage in it.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;– Henry Ford&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in the day, when I was going through University I worked as a labourer from time to time for a good friend of mine Cam. Cam ran his own building company and I did occasional work when business was busy or an extra pair of hands was needed to hold a nail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day over lunch, after a typical physical morning labouring Cam asked me “how I was going?”. I gave the usual “Good”. Which he followed up with “so, what do you like about the job?”. My reply, “I like that I don’t have to think, I can put my head down and do my job. And before I know it the day is over”. Cam’s reply has stuck with me to this day, almost 20 years later, “wrong! I pay you to think. I expect you to think.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Think like a man of action, act like a man of thought.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;– Henri Bergson&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is something I bring up in my own way when talking to the guys and girls building the project. It does not take a four year degree to think. Just because an engineer has been to University does not mean they have the answer. I remind them of the lesson I was taught, that no mater your role we are all paid to think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If everyone is thinking alike, then somebody isn’t thinking.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;– George S. Patton&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all have a unique view — perspective — and we are all paid to think for ourselves. Some people do not want to think, some do not believe they are smart enough.  As a manager you need to create an environment where thinking is acknowledged and rewarded. It is hard to get free thinking out of mindless robots, out of people that are micro managed. So take the time to explain why the task they are doing is important, how it fits into the big picture and take every opportunity up-skill and reward people that are self motivated, consciousness and want to be there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I have always found that the man whose second thoughts are good is worth watching.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;James M. Barrie&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-book.html&quot;&gt;Engineering Rule Book&lt;/a&gt; for the other rules.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ian Teda</name><email>ian@teda.id.au</email></author><category term="engineering" /><category term="construction" /><category term="rule-book" /><summary type="html">Thinking is the hardest work there is, which is probably the reason why so few engage in it.– Henry Ford Back in the day, when I was going through University I worked as a labourer from time to time for a good friend of mine Cam. Cam ran his own building company and I did occasional work when business was busy or an extra pair of hands was needed to hold a nail. One day over lunch, after a typical physical morning labouring Cam asked me “how I was going?”. I gave the usual “Good”. Which he followed up with “so, what do you like about the job?”. My reply, “I like that I don’t have to think, I can put my head down and do my job. And before I know it the day is over”. Cam’s reply has stuck with me to this day, almost 20 years later, “wrong! I pay you to think. I expect you to think.” Think like a man of action, act like a man of thought.– Henri Bergson It is something I bring up in my own way when talking to the guys and girls building the project. It does not take a four year degree to think. Just because an engineer has been to University does not mean they have the answer. I remind them of the lesson I was taught, that no mater your role we are all paid to think. If everyone is thinking alike, then somebody isn’t thinking.– George S. Patton We all have a unique view — perspective — and we are all paid to think for ourselves. Some people do not want to think, some do not believe they are smart enough. As a manager you need to create an environment where thinking is acknowledged and rewarded. It is hard to get free thinking out of mindless robots, out of people that are micro managed. So take the time to explain why the task they are doing is important, how it fits into the big picture and take every opportunity up-skill and reward people that are self motivated, consciousness and want to be there. I have always found that the man whose second thoughts are good is worth watching.James M. Barrie Check out the Engineering Rule Book for the other rules.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rule 14 - The KISS Principle</title><link href="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-14-kiss-principle.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rule 14 - The KISS Principle" /><published>2017-06-20T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-06-20T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-14-kiss-principle</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-14-kiss-principle.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Simplicity is the ultimate sophistication.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;– Leonardo da Vinci&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep It Simple Stupid (KISS).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It isn’t hard to make things difficult, anybody can do that. Even someone stupid. The skill and art, is in making it simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simple is: the essence; the most important part; something that is repeatable; provides the same outcome; that if you remember anything, remember this;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The KISS principle was first adopted by the US Navy&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:navy&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:navy&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, for the design of their naval ships. With the premise being, the more complex a ship is the more likely it is to breakdown and the harder it will be to maintain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Keep it simple, when you get too complex you forget the obvious. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;— Al McGuire&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not only true for ships, but any process, system or design. By keeping your work process simple, you are heading towards an error-free work environment. Meaning there is a decreased chance of a safety, quality or environmental incident. And if there is a failure in the process, it is less likely to have a severe consequence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep your workflow simple, there is less chance of things going wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Life’s like art. You have to work hard to keep it simple and still have meaning.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;– Charles de Lint&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a guiding principle, design should aim to avoid complexity. The most important part of keeping a design simple, is being consistent within the design. The more variants in a solution, the more complex a design gets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aim to provide a solution that can be utilised in as many scenarios as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you can’t explain it simply, you don’t understand it well enough.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;— Albert Einstein&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You never really understand something, until you have to teach it to someone. Because it forces you to articulate a concept. It has the side-effect of reducing the concept to its most simple key elements in a logical order. So that the majority of people can understand what you are explaining.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If people don’t understand you, the chances are you haven’t simplified the concept enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It seems that perfection is reached not when there is nothing left to add, but when there is nothing left to take away. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt; Antoine de Saint Exupéry&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The principle is also true of writing. The art to a good article is being able to express yourself in as few words as possible. While not losing the essences of your message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-book.html&quot;&gt;Engineering Rule Book&lt;/a&gt; for the other rules.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:navy&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/KISS_principle&quot;&gt;KISS Principle&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:navy&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Ian Teda</name><email>ian@teda.id.au</email></author><category term="engineering" /><category term="construction" /><category term="rule-book" /><summary type="html">Simplicity is the ultimate sophistication.– Leonardo da Vinci Keep It Simple Stupid (KISS). It isn’t hard to make things difficult, anybody can do that. Even someone stupid. The skill and art, is in making it simple. Simple is: the essence; the most important part; something that is repeatable; provides the same outcome; that if you remember anything, remember this; The KISS principle was first adopted by the US Navy1, for the design of their naval ships. With the premise being, the more complex a ship is the more likely it is to breakdown and the harder it will be to maintain. Keep it simple, when you get too complex you forget the obvious. — Al McGuire It is not only true for ships, but any process, system or design. By keeping your work process simple, you are heading towards an error-free work environment. Meaning there is a decreased chance of a safety, quality or environmental incident. And if there is a failure in the process, it is less likely to have a severe consequence. Keep your workflow simple, there is less chance of things going wrong. Life’s like art. You have to work hard to keep it simple and still have meaning.– Charles de Lint As a guiding principle, design should aim to avoid complexity. The most important part of keeping a design simple, is being consistent within the design. The more variants in a solution, the more complex a design gets. Aim to provide a solution that can be utilised in as many scenarios as possible. If you can’t explain it simply, you don’t understand it well enough.— Albert Einstein You never really understand something, until you have to teach it to someone. Because it forces you to articulate a concept. It has the side-effect of reducing the concept to its most simple key elements in a logical order. So that the majority of people can understand what you are explaining. If people don’t understand you, the chances are you haven’t simplified the concept enough. It seems that perfection is reached not when there is nothing left to add, but when there is nothing left to take away. Antoine de Saint Exupéry The principle is also true of writing. The art to a good article is being able to express yourself in as few words as possible. While not losing the essences of your message. Check out the Engineering Rule Book for the other rules. KISS Principle&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8617;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rule 13 - Learn to ask good questions.</title><link href="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-13-good-questions.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rule 13 - Learn to ask good questions." /><published>2017-06-10T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-06-10T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-13-good-questions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-13-good-questions.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Successful people ask better questions, and as a result, they get better answers.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;– Tony Robbins&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questions are the cornerstone of communication – aka leadership, problem solving and learning. So being able to ask good questions is the key to good communication, efficient problem solving and effective learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an art to asking a good questions, because after all if you put garbage in you get garbage out. If people are giving you the wrong answers, the chances are you are asking the wrong questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;open-ended-questions--communication&quot;&gt;Open-Ended Questions – Communication&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is not the answer that enlightens, but the question.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;– Decouvertes&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An open-ended question is question that has a non yes-or-no answer. Open-ended questions invite people into a conversation and make them articulate their point of view, give you their opinions and share their feelings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are particularly useful when approaching safety corners. Instead of asking “Do you think that is safe?”, ask “When you went through your project induction, what did you discuss about ladders?” or “Explain to me what a Job Safety Analysis Card is?”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open ended questions can be a little uncomfortable, because they appear to hand control of the conversation to the respondent&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:changeminds&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:changeminds&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. This is where the art of a good question comes in. Plan your questions, know your end, frame it for the respondent, use neutral words, focus for one answer, don’t interrupt, listen and use there answer to transition to the next question. Building the conversation so that in the end they feel like the idea or make the statement you are leading them towards is theres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Are you able to explain to me what a Job Safety Analysis Card is?”, “Awesome, what was on your teams JSA card this morning?”, and “Why do you think working from a ladder is dangerous?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When getting to know people and building relationships open-ended questions about them are a great way to build rapport. After all, we all love talking about ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-5-whys&quot;&gt;The 5 Why’s&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you do not ask the right questions, you do not get the right answers. A question asked in the right way often points to its own answer. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;— Edward Hodnett&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Toddlers love to ask why, over and over and over again. And so should you. Often the root cause to a problem can be found in the fifth why&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5whys&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5whys&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Start by defining the problem, then ask:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why did the problem just happen?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Yes, but why was that?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Yes, but why was that?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Yes, but why was that?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Yes, but why was that?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the five why’s, you will be a lot closer to understanding your problem. Asking why sounds simplistic, but it forces people to articulate their view. But ensure answers are based in truth, that it can be demonstrated. With each successive why, a layer of fluff is removed. Simplifying the groups understanding of the problem and its cause. The root cause can be found in the most simplistic explanation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;can-you-paraphrase-what-i-just-said&quot;&gt;Can you Paraphrase what I just Said?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For true success ask yourself these four questions: Why? Why not? Why not me? Why not now?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;— James Allen&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like to check-in when explaining something new to people, to help ensure understanding. It can be frustrating when someone walks away and you think they understand what needs to be done. Only to find out a couple of days later that they didn’t understand and missed the point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I check-in by asking them to paraphrase – repeat what I just said in there own words – what I have just explained or asked them to do. But keep in mind, if they don’t understand, the chances are you haven’t explained it good enough. So try again and again until they do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Question everything. Learn something. Answer nothing.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;— Engineer’s Motto&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-book.html&quot;&gt;Engineering Rule Book&lt;/a&gt; for the other rules.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:changeminds&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://changingminds.org/techniques/questioning/open_closed_questions.htm&quot;&gt;Open and Closed Questions&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:changeminds&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5whys&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mindtools.com/pages/article/newTMC_5W.htm&quot;&gt;5 Whys: Getting to the Root of a Problem Quickly&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5whys&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Ian Teda</name><email>ian@teda.id.au</email></author><category term="engineering" /><category term="construction" /><category term="rule-book" /><summary type="html">Successful people ask better questions, and as a result, they get better answers.– Tony Robbins Questions are the cornerstone of communication – aka leadership, problem solving and learning. So being able to ask good questions is the key to good communication, efficient problem solving and effective learning. There is an art to asking a good questions, because after all if you put garbage in you get garbage out. If people are giving you the wrong answers, the chances are you are asking the wrong questions. Open-Ended Questions – Communication It is not the answer that enlightens, but the question.– Decouvertes An open-ended question is question that has a non yes-or-no answer. Open-ended questions invite people into a conversation and make them articulate their point of view, give you their opinions and share their feelings. They are particularly useful when approaching safety corners. Instead of asking “Do you think that is safe?”, ask “When you went through your project induction, what did you discuss about ladders?” or “Explain to me what a Job Safety Analysis Card is?”. Open ended questions can be a little uncomfortable, because they appear to hand control of the conversation to the respondent1. This is where the art of a good question comes in. Plan your questions, know your end, frame it for the respondent, use neutral words, focus for one answer, don’t interrupt, listen and use there answer to transition to the next question. Building the conversation so that in the end they feel like the idea or make the statement you are leading them towards is theres. “Are you able to explain to me what a Job Safety Analysis Card is?”, “Awesome, what was on your teams JSA card this morning?”, and “Why do you think working from a ladder is dangerous?” When getting to know people and building relationships open-ended questions about them are a great way to build rapport. After all, we all love talking about ourselves. The 5 Why’s If you do not ask the right questions, you do not get the right answers. A question asked in the right way often points to its own answer. — Edward Hodnett Toddlers love to ask why, over and over and over again. And so should you. Often the root cause to a problem can be found in the fifth why2. Start by defining the problem, then ask: Why did the problem just happen? Yes, but why was that? Yes, but why was that? Yes, but why was that? Yes, but why was that? With the five why’s, you will be a lot closer to understanding your problem. Asking why sounds simplistic, but it forces people to articulate their view. But ensure answers are based in truth, that it can be demonstrated. With each successive why, a layer of fluff is removed. Simplifying the groups understanding of the problem and its cause. The root cause can be found in the most simplistic explanation. Can you Paraphrase what I just Said? For true success ask yourself these four questions: Why? Why not? Why not me? Why not now?— James Allen I like to check-in when explaining something new to people, to help ensure understanding. It can be frustrating when someone walks away and you think they understand what needs to be done. Only to find out a couple of days later that they didn’t understand and missed the point. I check-in by asking them to paraphrase – repeat what I just said in there own words – what I have just explained or asked them to do. But keep in mind, if they don’t understand, the chances are you haven’t explained it good enough. So try again and again until they do. Question everything. Learn something. Answer nothing.— Engineer’s Motto Check out the Engineering Rule Book for the other rules. Open and Closed Questions&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8617; 5 Whys: Getting to the Root of a Problem Quickly&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8617;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rule 12 - When you have the choice, always start with the hardest part.</title><link href="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-12-hard-things.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rule 12 - When you have the choice, always start with the hardest part." /><published>2017-06-02T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-06-02T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-12-hard-things</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-12-hard-things.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Sometimes the hardest thing and the right thing are the same.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;The Fray - All at Once&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anything worthwhile is hard. Because it is the difficulties that make it unique and it is the uniqueness that makes it valuable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Difficult roads often lead to beautiful destinations. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;- Unknown&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you have the choice, always start with the hardest part first. By achieving the hardest part first you gain a strategic and physiological advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strategically, you are de-risking the project by removing the biggest unknown on time, money and effort. The outcome of the project becomes more predictable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Physiologically, you are providing a proof case. If we can smash the hardest part, the rest is going to be easy. Lets get after it. We have made it up the hill and the rest is downhill. Awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-book.html&quot;&gt;Engineering Rule Book&lt;/a&gt; for the other rules.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ian Teda</name><email>ian@teda.id.au</email></author><category term="engineering" /><category term="construction" /><category term="rule-book" /><summary type="html">Sometimes the hardest thing and the right thing are the same.The Fray - All at Once Anything worthwhile is hard. Because it is the difficulties that make it unique and it is the uniqueness that makes it valuable. Difficult roads often lead to beautiful destinations. - Unknown When you have the choice, always start with the hardest part first. By achieving the hardest part first you gain a strategic and physiological advantage. Strategically, you are de-risking the project by removing the biggest unknown on time, money and effort. The outcome of the project becomes more predictable. Physiologically, you are providing a proof case. If we can smash the hardest part, the rest is going to be easy. Lets get after it. We have made it up the hill and the rest is downhill. Awesome. Check out the Engineering Rule Book for the other rules.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rule 11 - Finding Time</title><link href="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-11-finding-time.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rule 11 - Finding Time" /><published>2017-05-25T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-05-25T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-11-finding-time</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-11-finding-time.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Time is the measurer of all things, but is itself immeasurable, and the grand discloser of all things, but is itself undisclosed. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt; - Charles Caleb Colton&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It all boils down to time. After all, money is just the value we place on time. It makes sense then, that the most valuable gift you can give is your time. Because, we don’t know how much we have, we cannot make more of it and once it has turned into yesterday we cannot get it back. When we are young it seems to go on for ever and yet our time maybe up tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you love life, don’t waste time, for time is what life is made up of. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;- Bruce Lee&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If time is the most valuable thing we have, then it makes sense to maximise our return. How? Through the routine and discipline of prioritising our demands, executing on our priorities, measuring our output and adapting as needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are not the master of your time, then time will be the master of you - i.e. you will not have any. Routine is about setting up habits, rituals and behaviours to optimise your time. It is the discipline in these routines that gives you freedom, the freedom to choose what we do with our time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Time is free, but its priceless. You can’t own it, but you can use it. You can’t keep it, but you can spend it. Once you’ve lost it, you can never get it back. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;- Harvey Mackay&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step in prioritising your time is to apply the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pareto_principle&quot;&gt;Pareto Principle&lt;/a&gt;. Research has shown that
80% of your output will typically comes from 20% of your input. With that in mind you need to figure out what your 20% input is and delegate as much of the remainder of your input as possible. Leaving you time to improve the quality of your 80% output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A man who dares to waste one hour of time has not discovered the value of life. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;- Charles Darwin&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favourite tool to manage my time (priorities) is the &lt;a href=&quot;http://bulletjournal.com/&quot;&gt;bullet journal&lt;/a&gt;. To quote the Bullet Journal website, it is &lt;em&gt;“the analog system for the digital age. The Bullet Journal is a customizable and forgiving organization system. It can be your to-do list, sketchbook, notebook, and diary, but most likely, it will be all of the above. It will teach you to do more with less.”&lt;/em&gt; I would call myself a digital kind of person, but there is something about writing things down and the customisable nature of paper that has won me over. I have been using it for two years now and think it is the best tool for solidifying thoughts, remembering tasks, prioritising demands and tracking output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The strongest of all warriors are these two — Time and Patience. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;- Leo Tolstoy&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is safe to say that you cannot make a baby with nine women in one month. That sometimes things take, what they take and putting more resources on it will not accelerate time. So you need to deploy a little patience, with some determination thrown in. You can always throw an extra scraper fleet info it, but a D11 can only do so many pushes an hour. Meaning you can physically only fit so many scrapers into the one area and a D11 can only push so many 651s per hour. This is particularly true when it comes to changing groups of people, changing cultural habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Yesterday is gone. Tomorrow has not yet come. We have only today. Let us begin. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;- Mother Teresa&lt;cite&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Question:&lt;/em&gt; How do you find time?
&lt;em&gt;Answer:&lt;/em&gt; Take control of your time, to find time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Time is, time was, but time shall be no more. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;- James Joyce&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-book.html&quot;&gt;Engineering Rule Book&lt;/a&gt; for the other rules.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ian Teda</name><email>ian@teda.id.au</email></author><category term="engineering" /><category term="construction" /><category term="rule-book" /><summary type="html">Time is the measurer of all things, but is itself immeasurable, and the grand discloser of all things, but is itself undisclosed. - Charles Caleb Colton It all boils down to time. After all, money is just the value we place on time. It makes sense then, that the most valuable gift you can give is your time. Because, we don’t know how much we have, we cannot make more of it and once it has turned into yesterday we cannot get it back. When we are young it seems to go on for ever and yet our time maybe up tomorrow. If you love life, don’t waste time, for time is what life is made up of. - Bruce Lee If time is the most valuable thing we have, then it makes sense to maximise our return. How? Through the routine and discipline of prioritising our demands, executing on our priorities, measuring our output and adapting as needed. If you are not the master of your time, then time will be the master of you - i.e. you will not have any. Routine is about setting up habits, rituals and behaviours to optimise your time. It is the discipline in these routines that gives you freedom, the freedom to choose what we do with our time. Time is free, but its priceless. You can’t own it, but you can use it. You can’t keep it, but you can spend it. Once you’ve lost it, you can never get it back. - Harvey Mackay The first step in prioritising your time is to apply the Pareto Principle. Research has shown that 80% of your output will typically comes from 20% of your input. With that in mind you need to figure out what your 20% input is and delegate as much of the remainder of your input as possible. Leaving you time to improve the quality of your 80% output. A man who dares to waste one hour of time has not discovered the value of life. - Charles Darwin My favourite tool to manage my time (priorities) is the bullet journal. To quote the Bullet Journal website, it is “the analog system for the digital age. The Bullet Journal is a customizable and forgiving organization system. It can be your to-do list, sketchbook, notebook, and diary, but most likely, it will be all of the above. It will teach you to do more with less.” I would call myself a digital kind of person, but there is something about writing things down and the customisable nature of paper that has won me over. I have been using it for two years now and think it is the best tool for solidifying thoughts, remembering tasks, prioritising demands and tracking output. The strongest of all warriors are these two — Time and Patience. - Leo Tolstoy It is safe to say that you cannot make a baby with nine women in one month. That sometimes things take, what they take and putting more resources on it will not accelerate time. So you need to deploy a little patience, with some determination thrown in. You can always throw an extra scraper fleet info it, but a D11 can only do so many pushes an hour. Meaning you can physically only fit so many scrapers into the one area and a D11 can only push so many 651s per hour. This is particularly true when it comes to changing groups of people, changing cultural habits. Yesterday is gone. Tomorrow has not yet come. We have only today. Let us begin. - Mother Teresa Question: How do you find time? Answer: Take control of your time, to find time. Time is, time was, but time shall be no more. - James Joyce Check out the Engineering Rule Book for the other rules.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rule 10 - Pop quiz, what is the number?</title><link href="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-10-pop-quiz.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rule 10 - Pop quiz, what is the number?" /><published>2017-05-18T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-05-18T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-10-pop-quiz</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-10-pop-quiz.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You don’t know, what you don’t know.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;- Unknown&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Never have truer words been spoken. It is always the unknown unknowns that get you. Because they blind side you when you are looking the other way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What gets measured gets managed.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;- Peter Drucker&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want people to focus on something, ask them to measure it. And pop quiz them each day about what the number is. The pop quiz will help:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Force them to understand what is going on&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:rule3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:rule3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Give you a level of confidence they have the situation under control. If from day to day they know how the number has changed and why;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reinforce that this is important to you;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Allow you adapt sooner to changes. With the level of detail or how often you measure being relative to the complexity and size;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Measurement is fabulous. Unless you are busy measuring what is easy to measure as opposed to what’s important.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;  - Seth Godin&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worried about not meeting program: measure how many m3 of concrete have gone in, tonnes of reinforcement or dollars spent to date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worried about the budget: measure man hours, plant hours or wastage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One accurate measurement, is worth a thousand expert opinions.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;- Unknown&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best tool I have found for measuring on construction projects is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earned_value_management&quot;&gt;Earn Value Analysis (EVA)&lt;/a&gt;. It allows you to measure scope, time and costs against planned work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you don’t know how your are performing relative to the plan, how do you know when you are off track and need correction?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt; - Personal&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-book.html&quot;&gt;Engineering Rule Book&lt;/a&gt; for the other rules.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:rule3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-3-dont-give-me-surprises.html&quot;&gt;Rule 3 - Give me good news, give bad news. Just don’t give me surprises&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:rule3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Ian Teda</name><email>ian@teda.id.au</email></author><category term="engineering" /><category term="construction" /><category term="rule-book" /><summary type="html">You don’t know, what you don’t know.- Unknown Never have truer words been spoken. It is always the unknown unknowns that get you. Because they blind side you when you are looking the other way. What gets measured gets managed.- Peter Drucker If you want people to focus on something, ask them to measure it. And pop quiz them each day about what the number is. The pop quiz will help: Force them to understand what is going on1; Give you a level of confidence they have the situation under control. If from day to day they know how the number has changed and why; Reinforce that this is important to you; Allow you adapt sooner to changes. With the level of detail or how often you measure being relative to the complexity and size; Measurement is fabulous. Unless you are busy measuring what is easy to measure as opposed to what’s important. - Seth Godin Worried about not meeting program: measure how many m3 of concrete have gone in, tonnes of reinforcement or dollars spent to date. Worried about the budget: measure man hours, plant hours or wastage. One accurate measurement, is worth a thousand expert opinions.- Unknown The best tool I have found for measuring on construction projects is Earn Value Analysis (EVA). It allows you to measure scope, time and costs against planned work. If you don’t know how your are performing relative to the plan, how do you know when you are off track and need correction? - Personal Check out the Engineering Rule Book for the other rules. Rule 3 - Give me good news, give bad news. Just don’t give me surprises&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8617;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rule 9 - Always start with the end in mind.</title><link href="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-9-always-start-with-the-end-in-mind.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rule 9 - Always start with the end in mind." /><published>2017-05-10T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-05-10T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-9-always-start-with-the-end-in-mind</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-9-always-start-with-the-end-in-mind.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I can’t change the direction of the wind, but I can adjust my sails to always reach my destination. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;– Jimmy Dean&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Always start with the end in mind. What is the ideal outcome? What is your destination? And then breakdown the journey into manageable pieces, reverse engineering the path to get there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t have a destination, you don’t have direction. And if you don’t have direction you are lost, going around and around in circles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By prevailing over all obstacles and distractions, one may unfailingly arrive at his chosen goal or destination. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;– Christopher Columbus&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The path isn’t always clear, because the path is not always well traveled. But with an end in mind, a good internal compass and a belief in self you can reach your destination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good internal compass is about optimism. The optimism that the destination is achievable, even when the path isn’t clear. But a good internal compass is not just about optimism, it is also about having enough self awareness to know when a correction is needed. To know when you have strayed off course and need to get back on the path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The path less traveled can be dangerous, it is uncharted and filled with traps. And when pioneering, when innovating often you will need to be the first to taste the berries and hope they are not poisonous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To become ‘unique,’ the challenge is to fight the hardest battle which anyone can imagine until you reach your destination. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;– A. P. J. Abdul Kalam&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-book.html&quot;&gt;Engineering Rule Book&lt;/a&gt; for the other rules.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ian Teda</name><email>ian@teda.id.au</email></author><category term="engineering" /><category term="construction" /><category term="rule-book" /><summary type="html">I can’t change the direction of the wind, but I can adjust my sails to always reach my destination. – Jimmy Dean Always start with the end in mind. What is the ideal outcome? What is your destination? And then breakdown the journey into manageable pieces, reverse engineering the path to get there. If you don’t have a destination, you don’t have direction. And if you don’t have direction you are lost, going around and around in circles. By prevailing over all obstacles and distractions, one may unfailingly arrive at his chosen goal or destination. – Christopher Columbus The path isn’t always clear, because the path is not always well traveled. But with an end in mind, a good internal compass and a belief in self you can reach your destination. A good internal compass is about optimism. The optimism that the destination is achievable, even when the path isn’t clear. But a good internal compass is not just about optimism, it is also about having enough self awareness to know when a correction is needed. To know when you have strayed off course and need to get back on the path. The path less traveled can be dangerous, it is uncharted and filled with traps. And when pioneering, when innovating often you will need to be the first to taste the berries and hope they are not poisonous. To become ‘unique,’ the challenge is to fight the hardest battle which anyone can imagine until you reach your destination. – A. P. J. Abdul Kalam Check out the Engineering Rule Book for the other rules.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rule 8 - Keep one eye open and your ear to the ground.</title><link href="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-8-eye-and-ear.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rule 8 - Keep one eye open and your ear to the ground." /><published>2017-05-03T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-05-03T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-8-eye-and-ear</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-8-eye-and-ear.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Blinding ignorance does mislead us. O! Wretched mortals, open your eyes! &lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt;- Leonardo da Vinci&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is easy to focus on your work and for your work to become your world. But it is equally important to keep the bigger picture in mind and maintain perspective. To learn the context of where your work fits into the bigger machine, what external forces could effect your work and how you might be able to help others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, take the long slow way around site. Keeping one eye open, observing what others are doing. And your ear to the ground, listening to what others are saying in meetings and in conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By doing this you are able to answer more questions, know the right person to ask your question and where to find that stock N16 bar when you under order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Rule 8 - Keep One Eye Open and Your Ear to the Ground&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-book.html&quot;&gt;Engineering Rule Book&lt;/a&gt; for the other rules.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ian Teda</name><email>ian@teda.id.au</email></author><category term="engineering" /><category term="construction" /><category term="rule-book" /><summary type="html">Blinding ignorance does mislead us. O! Wretched mortals, open your eyes! - Leonardo da Vinci It is easy to focus on your work and for your work to become your world. But it is equally important to keep the bigger picture in mind and maintain perspective. To learn the context of where your work fits into the bigger machine, what external forces could effect your work and how you might be able to help others. With that in mind, take the long slow way around site. Keeping one eye open, observing what others are doing. And your ear to the ground, listening to what others are saying in meetings and in conversation. By doing this you are able to answer more questions, know the right person to ask your question and where to find that stock N16 bar when you under order. Rule 8 - Keep One Eye Open and Your Ear to the Ground Check out the Engineering Rule Book for the other rules.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rule 7 - Do not walk past it.</title><link href="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-7-do-not-walk-past-it.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rule 7 - Do not walk past it." /><published>2017-04-25T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-04-25T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-7-do-not-walk-past-it</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-7-do-not-walk-past-it.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The standard you walk past, is the standard you accept. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt; - David Morrison&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be it a safety concern, poor workmanship or bad behaviour if you close your eyes and walk past it then you are accepting it. You are saying that you are not concerned and feel free to keep doing it without correction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To live by this rule means difficult conversations, extra work and extra responsibility. Not everyone goes looking for or wants these things. But ignoring this rule leads to regret, disappointment and mediocrity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Big problems can often be avoid by addressing small problems that come past you. So don’t ignore the small problems, by walking past them. Instead get out in front of them and avoid the big ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-book.html&quot;&gt;Engineering Rule Book&lt;/a&gt; for the other rules.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ian Teda</name><email>ian@teda.id.au</email></author><category term="engineering" /><category term="construction" /><category term="rule-book" /><summary type="html">The standard you walk past, is the standard you accept. - David Morrison Be it a safety concern, poor workmanship or bad behaviour if you close your eyes and walk past it then you are accepting it. You are saying that you are not concerned and feel free to keep doing it without correction. To live by this rule means difficult conversations, extra work and extra responsibility. Not everyone goes looking for or wants these things. But ignoring this rule leads to regret, disappointment and mediocrity. Big problems can often be avoid by addressing small problems that come past you. So don’t ignore the small problems, by walking past them. Instead get out in front of them and avoid the big ones. Check out the Engineering Rule Book for the other rules.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rule 6 - Respect the 6 Ps.</title><link href="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-6-the-6-ps.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rule 6 - Respect the 6 Ps." /><published>2017-04-20T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2017-04-20T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-6-the-6-ps</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-6-the-6-ps.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The 6 Ps: Prior Planning Prevents Piss Poor Performance. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt; - U.S. Army&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Respect the 6 Ps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prior&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Planning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prevents&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Piss&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Poor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Performance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1---prior&quot;&gt;1 - Prior&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Give me six hours to chop down a tree and I will spend the first four sharpening the axe. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt; - Abraham Lincoln&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t leave your planning to the last moment. Insteed, dive into the detail early to make sure a lack of planning doesn’t become somebody else’s priority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2---planning&quot;&gt;2 - Planning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A goal without a plan is just a wish!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pictures! There is a reason why we build of drawings. And planning should be no different. Make drawings, sketches and slides to convey your message, the mental picture of how it is going to be built. Your vision if you would.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3---prevents&quot;&gt;3 - Prevents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A plan that everyone dislikes for different reasons is a success. A plan everyone dislikes for the same reason is a failure. And a plan that everyone likes for the same reason is an act of God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ensure understanding of your vision by asking for feedback. And be humble enough to accept criticsm and adapt your plan as needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4---piss&quot;&gt;4 - Piss&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There are two kinds of failures: those who thought and never did, and those who did and never thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consult grey haired people. This isn’t the first time, so learn from other peoples mistakes and avoid mistakes of the past. Search out common school boy errors and plan around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5---poor&quot;&gt;5 - Poor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Those who fail to plan, plans to fail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You never really learn something until you have to teach it. So the best way to understand howto build something is to try and explain it to someone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6---performance&quot;&gt;6 - Performance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Poor planning or poor execution of plans is simply to let some force other than reason shape reality. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;cite&gt; - Robert McNamara&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can spend your time putting out fires, or you can spent your time planning and adapting. If you spend all your time putting out fires, then for the most part your destiny is being set by other forces outside your control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ianteda.com/engineering/rule-book.html&quot;&gt;Engineering Rule Book&lt;/a&gt; for the other rules.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ian Teda</name><email>ian@teda.id.au</email></author><category term="engineering" /><category term="construction" /><category term="rule-book" /><summary type="html">The 6 Ps: Prior Planning Prevents Piss Poor Performance. - U.S. Army Respect the 6 Ps: Prior Planning Prevents Piss Poor Performance 1 - Prior Give me six hours to chop down a tree and I will spend the first four sharpening the axe. - Abraham Lincoln Don’t leave your planning to the last moment. Insteed, dive into the detail early to make sure a lack of planning doesn’t become somebody else’s priority. 2 - Planning A goal without a plan is just a wish! Pictures! There is a reason why we build of drawings. And planning should be no different. Make drawings, sketches and slides to convey your message, the mental picture of how it is going to be built. Your vision if you would. 3 - Prevents A plan that everyone dislikes for different reasons is a success. A plan everyone dislikes for the same reason is a failure. And a plan that everyone likes for the same reason is an act of God. Ensure understanding of your vision by asking for feedback. And be humble enough to accept criticsm and adapt your plan as needed. 4 - Piss There are two kinds of failures: those who thought and never did, and those who did and never thought. Consult grey haired people. This isn’t the first time, so learn from other peoples mistakes and avoid mistakes of the past. Search out common school boy errors and plan around. 5 - Poor Those who fail to plan, plans to fail. You never really learn something until you have to teach it. So the best way to understand howto build something is to try and explain it to someone else. 6 - Performance Poor planning or poor execution of plans is simply to let some force other than reason shape reality. - Robert McNamara You can spend your time putting out fires, or you can spent your time planning and adapting. If you spend all your time putting out fires, then for the most part your destiny is being set by other forces outside your control. Check out the Engineering Rule Book for the other rules.</summary></entry></feed>